Guide to the Artists' Fund Society Records 1859-1937 MS 23
New-York Historical Society
Artists' Fund Society records
1859-1937
New-York Historical Society
Artists' Fund Society of the City of New York
MS 23
5.5 Linear feet (10 boxes and 13 bound volumes)
The collection documents the history of the Artists' Fund Society, a New York based organization founded in 1859 to assist members and their families in cases of illness, old age and death; and to provide aid to non-member artists in distress. It includes meeting minutes, reports, membership materials, financial records, and correspondence.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection is made up of two acquisitions:
1. The papers of Alexander C. Morgan, Series I, President of the Artists' Fund Society from 1910-1933, acquired in 1941.
2. Artists' Fund Society records, Series II through X, donated by the Society of Illustrators in 2008.
Arrangement
The collection is organized in ten series:
Series I: Alexander C. Morgan Papers
Series II: Constitution and Amendments
Series III: Minutes
Series IV: Reports
Series V: Correspondence
Series VI: Membership
Series VII: Financial
Series VIII: Real Estate
Series IX: Art Exhibitions and Sales
Series X: Other Artists' Funds
Series I contains the papers of Alexander C. Morgan, a financier and amateur artist who served as president of the Artists' Fund Society from 1910-1932.
Series II through X contain Artists' Fund Society records (1859-1937) arranged by type.
Historical Note
During the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, millions of Americans received life insurance and other social welfare benefits through fraternal and mutual aid societies. The Artists' Fund Society was one such society. It was founded on February 5th, 1859, and incorporated on April 13, 1861. The primary mission of the organization was to provide aid to members experiencing disablement, sickness and distress, and to provide assistance to the widows, children and families of deceased members. In 1862 the Society additionally created a benevolent fund to provide aid to artists who were not members.
The original constitution of 1859 simply stated that members were required to be "artists by profession." However, by the 1930s amendments stipulated that members must live in New York City or close enough to attend meetings, and that no person over the age of 45 could become a member.
The organization's leadership consisted of a "Board of Control" comprised of a president, vice-president, secretary, treasurer and five other members. The Board of Control met monthly, and the Society sponsored an Annual Meeting for all members followed by an Annual Dinner for members and friends.
From 1860 through 1889, members were required to annually contribute a piece of art work to be exhibited and sold at auction. Money from the sales was deposited in a Special Investment Fund. Investments were made on first class bonds and mortgages and stocks of the United States and State of New York. Widows were paid annual interest on a sum of $1500, and then paid a lump sum of $1500 when their youngest child reached age 21. (The sum was raised over the years per amendments to the Constitution.)
In 1890, the system of selling art work was replaced with a system of "assessments." The Society required members to pay an assessment fee of $5 within 30 days of the death of a member; the beneficiary of the member received a percentage of the total amount collected.
Records indicate that in 1936 the Board of Control was considering re-organizing or dissolving the Society due to an increase in the number of members unable to pay their assessments, difficulty finding new young members and "a general lack of interest in the society." A decade later, in 1946, the Artists' Fund Society was formally consolidated with the Society of Illustrators, Inc.
Related Materials
Quadriennial, Biennal and Annual Reports of the Artists' Fund Society can be found in the New-York Historical Society's Library.
The Princeton University Library, Department of Rare Books and Special Collections, has a set of Artists' Fund Society sale catalogues, 1860-1889.
Scope and Contents
The collection offers insight into the mission and operation of a New York based mutual aid society for artists. The records span from the Society's founding in 1859 through 1937, a decade before it consolidated with the Society of Illustrators.
The records document the organization's structure, decision making, and finances. Meeting minutes, reports, amendments to the constitution, correspondence, resignations, wills, and financial records all demonstrate how the organization operated and changed over time.
Much of the correspondence in the collection describes the conditions of artists in need of help, including struggles with illness, disability, and economic hardship.
Sales ledgers documenting annual art auctions from 1861 to 1889 include artist names, titles of paintings, names of purchasers, and purchase prices.
Series I of the collection consists of the papers of Alexander C. Morgan, a long time member of the Society who served as president from 1910 through 1933. Series II through X are made up of Society records arranged by type. Morgan's papers were acquired by the New-York Historical Society in 1941; the rest of the materials were donated by the Society of Illustrators in 2008.
Agreements; Bankbooks.; Bank statements.; Checkbooks; Checks (bank checks); Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Financial records.; Minutes (administrative records); Receipts (financial records); Registers (lists); Reports.; Artists -- New York (State).; Artists -- Pensions -- New York (State).; Charities -- New York (State) -- New York.; Fraternal organizations -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social conditions.; Dunsmore, John Ward; Falconer, John Mackie, 1820-1903; Morgan, Alexander C.; Fund for Superannuated Artists (New York, N.Y.)
- Series I: Alexander C. Morgan Papers, 1881-1936
  Scope and Content Note
  Series 1 consists of the papers of Alexander C. Morgan, arranged in 6 subseries: a) Correspondence b) Relief Cases c) Membership d) Related Artists' Fund Societies e) Financial and Real Estate and f) Notes and Clippings.
  Morgan (1849-1933) was a financier and amateur landscape painter who served as president of the Artists' Fund Society from 1910-1933. A cousin of J. P. Morgan, he entered the stock brokerage business at an early age and founded the firm A.C. Morgan & Co., serving as its head until 1928. He was a founder of the Salmagundi Club, a life member of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, and a fellow in perpetuity of the National Academy of Design. His artwork was exhibited at a number of private showings.
  - Subseries A: Correspondence
    Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Letters consist largely of requests for assistance and thank you letters. Letters requesting assistance describe conditions of poverty, disability, illness, and old age, and are written by the artists themselves, as well as by family members, friends and charitable organizations on their behalf. Correspondents include John Ward Dunsmore, Secretary of the Artists' Fund Society, and William Merritt Post, Treasurer of the Artists' Fund Society.
    - Anderson-Aylward, 1923-1933 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Dunsmore-Dutton, 1924-1933 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Berneker-Buehler, 1929-1933 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Chapman-Dewey, 1923-1931 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Finley-French, 1926-1933 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Granville-Isador, 1925-1932 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Jackson-Loweth, 1924-1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - MacDowell-Nichols, 1927-1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Nordell-Phelps, 1925-1933 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Post, 1923-1933 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Potthast-Price, 1925-1932 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Raynor-Streatfeild, 1925-1933 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Tompkins-Winsor, 1929-1933 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Subseries B: Relief Cases
    This bound volume documents aid to artists provided by the Artists' Fund Society. It includes an alphabetized list of recipients followed by brief descriptions of each artist's circumstances and actions taken by the Society to provide help.
    - Relief Cases, Board of Control, 1931-1933 (Volume 1)
  - Subseries C: Membership
    These records document activities of the membership and legal agreements pertaining to assistance to families of deceased members. The Artists' Fund Society souvenir includes a small landscape painting by Arthur E. Powell.
    - Annual Dinner Souvenir and Ephemera, 1911 and undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Meeting Notices, 1924-1933 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Wills and Estates, 1923-1931 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Subseries D: Related Artist Fund Societies
    The Fund for Superannuated Artists was established in the early 1900s to assist aged artists in maintaining suitable homes. It was founded by members of the Artists' Fund Society and the Artists' Aid Society, and in 1932 it dissolved, dividing its money between the two organizations. Correspondence, meeting minutes, notes and memorandums document this history and the 1932 agreement.
    - Fund for Superannuated Artists, 1923-1932 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Subseries E: Financial and Real Estate
    The majority of these records document the Society's real estate investments.
    - Bills and Receipts, 1920-1931 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Mortgages, Becker-Kertyczak, 1923-1934 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Mortgages, Marx-Villosio, 1924-1934 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Real Estate Documents, 1924-1933 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Subseries F: Notes and Clippings
    This subseries consists largely of Morgan's hand written notes. A small quantity of newspaper clippings document Artists' Fund Society activities and external developments impacting the Society.
    - Newspaper Clippings, 1881-1933 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Notes (Hand Written), 1926-1933 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Series II: Constitution and Amendments
  This series consists of multiple versions of the constitution (printed and hand written), as well as proposals to amend the constitution over the years.
  - Constitution (Hand Written), 1859 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Constitution (Printed), 1859 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Constitution (Printed), Circa 1860 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Amendments and Resolutions, 1860 June 6-1936 March 12 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Series III: Minutes
  Meeting minutes are hand written and arranged chronologically in bound volumes. They are continuous from February 5, 1859 through April 1, 1873 and from February 8, 1876 through March 12, 1922. They include annual and quarterly (or later, "semi-annual") meetings of the membership, as well as monthly meetings of the Board of Control. Business discussed includes nomination and election of general and board members, financial investments, aid to members and non-members, planning of annual exhibits and dinners, and proposals to amend the constitution. Officers and names of those present are listed for each meeting.
  - Minutes, 1859 February 5-1873 April 1 (Volume 2)
  - Minutes, 1876 February 8-1885 May 5 (Volume 3)
  - Minutes, 1885 May 12-1897 April 13 (Volume 4)
  - Minutes, 1897 April 20-1922 March 12 (Volume 5)
- Series IV: Reports
  Reports are grouped by type. With the exception of Biennial Reports (which were formally published), most of these reports are hand written or typed drafts with hand written corrections and notations. The presidential and secretarial reports appear to be speeches that were read at the annual meeting or dinner. These reports discuss the overall health and activities of the organization, note deaths of members, and welcome new members.
  - Biennial Reports, 1916 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Leaflets, Circa 1888 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Nominations Committee Reports, 1896-1930 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - President's Reports, 1895-1900 and undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Secretary's Reports, 1917-1931 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Special Committee Reports, 1883-1916 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Treasurer and Auditor Reports, 1916-1923 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Treasurer and Auditor Reports, 1924-1937 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Series V: Correspondence
  This series consists of letters received by Artists' Fund Society officers and board members arranged alphabetically by recipient. Additionally, correspondence associated with particular committees and positions is grouped at the end. Letters address a range of activities and issues, including assistance to artists in need, updates on the health of those receiving aid, notifications of deaths of members, payment of assessment fees, honorary memberships, thank you letters, resignations, nominations for membership or service on the Board of Control, and other Society business.
  - de Forest, Lockwood, 1894-1905 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Department of Health, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Dunsmore, John Ward, 1925-1930 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Dunsmore, John Ward, 1931-1936 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Dustin, Silas, 1908-1909 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Falconer, John M., 1878 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Hicks, Thomas, 1876 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Hunt, Leigh, 1907-1909 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Post, William Merritt, 1910-1935 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Shurtleff, R. M., 1893 and undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Sindelar, T. A., 1914 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Williams, John Alonzo, 1935-1937 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Yewell, George H., 1892-1899 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Yewell, George H., 1900-1909 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Artists' Fund Society, General, 1888-1919 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Special Committee, 1885 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Board Members and Officers, 1860-1880 (Volume 6)
  - Treasurer, 1897-1906 (Volume 7)
- Series VI: Membership
  Lists, nominations, honorary memberships, notifications of member deaths, and resignations all track the composition and structure of Artists' Fund Society membership over time. Additionally, death of members and fees lists, designation of benefits forms, will and estate documents, and receipts documenting benefit payments all demonstrate how assistance was administered to widows, children and families of deceased members.
  - Annual Meeting and Dinner Notices, 1920-1924 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Death of Members and Fees List, 1903-1908 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Death of Members and Fees List, 1909-1933 (Volume 8)
  - Death of Members Notices, 1867-1905 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Death of Members Since 1925 List, Circa 1935 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Death of Members, Unpaid Assessments, 1935 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Designation of Benefits, Adams-Ennis, 1896-1932 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Designation of Benefits, Fassett-Loomis, 1896-1932 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Designation of Benefits, Macy-Ryder, 1896-1931 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Designation of Benefits, Sandor-Wood, 1896-1932 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Honorary Memberships, 1892 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Member Accounts and Dividends, 1860-1891 (Volume 14)
  - Membership List, Circa 1883-1934 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Membership List, Circa 1935 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1927 and undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Nominations for Membership, 1897-1921 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Receipt of Payment Upon Resignations and Deaths, 1885-1887 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Receipt of Payment Upon Deaths, 1914-1919 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Receipt of Payment Upon Deaths, 1932-1935 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Resignation Documents, 1885 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Resignation Documents, 1885 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Resignation Documents, 1886 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Resignation Documents, 1887 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Resignation Documents, 1888-1889 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Will and Estate Documents, 1881 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Will and Estate Documents, 1885-1887 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Will and Estate Documents, 1888 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Will and Estate Documents, 1889-1890 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Will and Estate Documents, 1904-1907 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Series VII: Financial
  This series is divided into two subseries.
  Subseries A, Financial Records, includes correspondence with banks, bank statements, bankbooks, canceled checks, and bills and receipts. There are five bound volumes, including a cash transaction book and four volumes of check stubs of the Second National Bank.
  Subseries B, John Mackie Falconer Papers, documents the investigation of J.M. Falconer, who served as Treasurer of the Artists' Fund Society from its inception until February 1883. Auditors determined that Falconer used deceptive record keeping practices to misappropriate $8,713.72. The final report on the affair said it was "the most painful and important" episode in the organization's history. These materials were bundled together by the Artists' Fund Society and are arranged in their own subseries to preserve this context.
  - Subseries A: Financial Records
    Financial Records include correspondence with banks, bank statements, bankbooks, canceled checks, and bills and receipts. There are five bound volumes, including a cash transaction book and four volumes of check stubs of the Second National Bank.
    - Bank Correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Bank Statements, 1929-1935 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Bankbooks, Manhattan Company, 1871-1881 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Bankbooks, National City Bank of New York, 1930-1934 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Bankbooks, Second National Bank, 1883-1922 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Bankbooks, Union Square Savings Bank, 1911-1936 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Bills and Receipts, 1879-1887 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Bills and Receipts, 1903-1910 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Bills and Receipts, 1911-1920 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Bills and Receipts, 1921-1929 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Bills and Receipts, 1930-1937 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Bills and Receipts (Blank Forms), undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Canceled Checks, 1879-1886 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Canceled Checks, 1908-1910 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Canceled Checks, 1922-1930 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Canceled Checks, 1931-1925 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Credits to Bank Accounts, 1906 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Credits to Bank Accounts, 1932-1937 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Dividend Payment Receipts, 1885-1886 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Notes (Hand Written), 1933-1934 and undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Safe Deposit Box Documents, 1931 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Cash Book, 1859-1891 (Volume 9)
    - Checks, Second National Bank, 1-300, 1883-1885 (Volume 10)
    - Checks, Second National Bank, 301-900, 1885-1890 (Volume 11)
    - Checks, Second National Bank, 1501-2000, 1912 April 10-1922 February 23 (Volume 12)
    - Checks, Second National Bank, 1252-1500, 1900-1912 (Volume 13)
  - Subseries B: John Mackie Falconer Papers
    This subseries documents the investgation of John Mackie Falconer, who served as Treasurer of the Artists' Fund Society from its inception until February 1883, when he was found guilty of misappropriating $8,713.72. These materials were bundled together by the Artists' Fund Society and are arranged in their own subseries to preserve this context.
    - Auditor Reports, 1882 November 14 - 1883 February 7 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence and Notes, 1882 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Legal Agreement, 1882 December 19 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Report on Falconer's Property, 1882 December 12 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Resignation Letters, 1883 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Treasury Reports by Falconer, 1861-1862 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Treasury Reports by Falconer, 1874-1881 (Box 9, Folder 4)
- Series VIII: Real Estate
  This series consists of correspondence, legal agreements, reports and other records documenting the Society's real estate investments.
  - Correspondence, 1924-1936 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Legal Agreements, 1897-1903 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Legal Agreements, 1912-1927 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Legal Agreements, 1930-1933 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Lists of Mortgages Held by the Artists' Fund Society, 1889-1934 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Memorandums, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Notes (Hand Written), undated (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Reports on Mortgage Company Reform, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 13)
- Series IX: Art Exhibitions and Sales
  From 1860 through 1889, members were required to annually contribute a piece of art work to be exhibited and sold at auction. Money from the sales was deposited in a Special Investment Fund used for life insurance benefits. This series contains ledgers documenting auction sales, including artist names, titles of paintings, names of purchasers, and purchase prices. It also contains notices to members regarding the logistics of the exhibitions, and an exhibit catalog from 1876.
  - Catalogs, 1876 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Notices to Members, 1868-1889 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Sales Ledgers, 1861-1867 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Sales Ledgers, 1871-1881 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Sales Ledgers, 1882-1889 (Box 10, Folder 3)
- Series X: Other Artists' Funds
  This series contains materials by and about other Artists' Funds in the United States, the United Kindgdom and Germany, including reports, pamphlets, invitations, newspaper clippings and correspondence.
  - Artists' Aid Society, 1910 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Artists' General Benevolent Institution, 1862-1904 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Fund for Superannuated Artists, 1904 and undated (Box 10, Folder 6)
    See Series I: Alexander C. Morgan, Subseries D, for more documents related to the Fund for Superannuated Artists. (link back to that section).
  - German Language Materials, 1863 (Box 10, Folder 7)